You've probably seen the thousands of
LinkedIn CEO posts saying that code is
cheap and they can move faster than ever
before. But what's happening is that AI
has simply accelerated software entropy.
In other words, codebases are falling
apart faster than they ever have before
because every time that you make a
change that doesn't take into account
the entire codebase, you are likely to
introduce little things, weird things
that make the codebase harder to change.
And over time, that just snowballs and
snowballs until you end up with a huge
ball of mud. Sloppy, sloppy mud that is
incredibly hard to reverse if you don't
know how to do it. I've made a video
about this before introducing folks to
the idea of deep modules. And that video
focuses more on prevention, how you can
prevent your setup from getting to that
point. Let's now focus on the cure, how
you can take a codebase that feels like
it's beyond repair and rescue it. And
you can do that with some good old
software fundamentals, as well as my
improved codebase architecture skill.
We're going to be walking through what
this skill does, revisiting some of the
terms we looked at in the other video,
then we're going to take that and apply
it to a real codebase. And this, by the
way, is part of my GitHub Skills Repo,
which is currently sitting at 41.5k
stars. Bonkers. Now, one of the things
that I added to this improved codebase
architecture skill recently was a
glossary of terminology. Having a shared
vocabulary with the AI is super
important because it means that you can
talk using the same language. You can
understand what each other's language is
and you can be a lot more precise with
what you're asking for. This terminology
here is super duper useful and I'm going
to spend a portion of this video going
through what each of these terms
actually mean. Honestly, just
understanding this stuff at a deep level
will make you a better software
developer. So, let's get started by
talking about modules. A module is a
unit of something in your application.
It could be a bunch of React components
that all fit together to form a page. It
could be a bunch of functions inside
your application that are entirely
responsible for authentication. Or it
could simply be the logger that you've
chosen, like a log into the console, log
into a file, or log into a third-party
service. In a good code base, these
modules talk to each other, and they
talk to each other via their interfaces.
An interface is everything a caller must
know to use the module correctly. For
instance, if it's an authentication
module, then it might have a sign-in
method, it might have a sign-out method.
And these methods are the interface to
that module. The methods are not the
only thing that's important, the
interface also includes kind of nebulous
information about how to call the
module. So, perhaps it's documentation,
too. The implementation is then what's
inside the module, what it actually does
when you call sign-in or sign-out. And
so, this is the core primitive that
we're talking about, the modules that
have interfaces and implementations
scattered throughout your application.
These modules can either be deep
modules, or they can be shallow modules.
A deep module hides lots of
implementation behind a relatively
simple interface. A shallow module has a
complex interface and kind of not much
implementation actually behind it. These
ideas are from John Osterhout's book A
Philosophy of Software Design, which I
recommend you pick up a copy of. Deep
modules are considered better than
shallow modules because it hides more
information away from the caller. In
other words, the person who's calling
this, or the function that's calling
this, only needs to know about this tiny
little interface, and they'll get access
to all of this implementation. Lovely.
And so, that's what we describe as
depth, the amount of behavior a caller
can exercise per unit of interface that
they have to learn. Really good
open-source libraries, like TanStack
Query or something, have really good
deep modules. In other words, they're
hiding a lot of complexity behind a
super simple interface. These modules
then interact with each other, and they
have dependencies on each other. For
instance, this module might interact
with this module here, which then
interacts with this module up here, and
this module up here, and they have these
dependency
are called the seams. It's the location
at which the modules interface lives
inside the application. These seams are
usually where you're going to do your
unit testing or your integration
testing. For instance, if we wanted to
test this module in isolation down here,
then we would add a mock or something
just at this seam. So, figuring out
where your seams are going to live in
your application is crucial to getting a
good architecture. When you find out
where a seam is in your application, you
need some concrete thing, a module, that
satisfies that interface. This is what
I'm going to call an adapter, which I'm
taking from hexagonal architecture. For
instance, if you have some kind of
application that depends on a clock
running, then you may want to have a
clock, a normal clock inside here using
the actual living clock, and then inside
some tests, you may want to have an
adapter that is a fake clock. These both
satisfy the interface at that seam, and
it means that you can use the fake clock
in tests, so you don't have to literally
wait 2 weeks for your test to finish.
So, that's how seams and adapters play
together. The benefit of all this is
that these deep modules have two main
properties or two main benefits that you
get from them. For the maintainers, the
people maintaining this module, they get
locality. Changes to that module and
bugs and all the fixes to do with them,
they concentrate in one place, in that
deep module. If it's scattered around
over multiple different modules, then
you have low locality. You want high
locality, grouping and co-locating the
things that matter and that often change
together. The people using this module
will get more leverage the deeper the
module is. In other words, more
capability per unit of interface they
have to learn. And so, when we're
talking about improving our code bases,
these are the two attributes that we're
aiming at. Right, that's enough
knowledge, we know the basic terms of
engagement. Now, let's go and improve a
code base. The code base we're going to
look at is my course video manager code
base, which is the repo of software that
I'm actually using to record this video.
This code base has had, ooh, around
1,500 commits here, and I wouldn't say
it's a ball of mud, but I also wouldn't
say it's perfect, either. It's a React
Router application, it uses effect.ts
under the hood. Uh, let's get into it.
I'm going to open up a new Claude
session inside here and I'm going to run
my improved code base architecture skill
and we'll turn off auto mode. Auto mode
does some funny things with these human
in the loop style flows and so I don't
want it on here. We can see it's going
and exploring and looking through the
code. That's what it's instructed to do
first. Here we go. Explore architecture
for deepening opportunities. Usually a
bad code base is one that has a ton of
shallow modules in it or one that has
very poor leverage for those modules or
poor locality where lots of stuff is
spread in lots of different places.
Okay, it's come back with some
candidates here. Let's bump up the
screen size and hopefully Claude code
won't just destroy itself. Okay, I guess
maybe we're not bumping up the screen
size. Thank you for that Claude code. We
can see it's identified six deepening
opportunities here. These candidates
here are pretty hard to explain because
they sort of require domain knowledge
about my repo, but we can see here that
it's saying that there's a concept that
doesn't have a single seam. In other
words, there are two implementations of
this insertion point and they live
and the seam where they must be
untested. This essentially means that
the front end could make some changes
but the back end because it has a
separate parallel implementation could
be out of sync with it. So this I think
is actually a really good candidate for
refactoring into a single module. We
gain locality. And it says that here we
would gain locality interleaved clip
clip section ordering rule lives in one
place. So let's go and take a look at
that. Let's actually say, yeah, I'd like
to pick one here. That seems like a good
candidate. So let's fire that off and
see what it says. Okay, Claude is
trolling me here. It says, I'd like to
pick one. I meant I meant one. Great.
Okay, so it now has come back with it's
got concrete code on both sides to to
ground this and it enters a grilling
session. And in this grilling session we
can take the ideas inside here and we
can start kind of talking about what a
better solution would be. This is a nice
sentence here. The back end has no end.
Let's not think about that too
literally. What you end up doing with
this skill is you end up talking about
the potential proposed solution, and it
will then propose a shape. And once
that's all done, you can take that and
you can put that in as a GitHub issue
into your issue tracker, which can then
be picked up by an AFK agent. You should
check out my video on Sandcastle if
you're interested in that. Now, in the
course of normal development, what I
would do is go through and thoughtfully
answer each of these questions in turn.
But since I'm doing a video and this is
slightly artificial, I'm going to say,
"Could you just choose your recommended
answers for each of these questions?"
And that should speed us through to
actually making the change or
potentially creating an issue out of
this. So, it's now coming back with a
proposed module shape, and it's also
asking to verify a particular part of
the implementation where end is
collapsed and to sketch the actual
TypeScript interface. Yeah, go ahead and
do both. That sounds great. Let's ping
that off and see what it says. Okay, it
has figured out the implementation
detail it needed, and it's come back and
proposed a design here. So, which of
these functions are going to be
essentially the uh the interface for
this module. And so, we can talk about
this with the AI and figure it out. It's
again come back with two design
decisions that it wants my feedback on.
And here, I think you've got the flavor
of how this skill works and the kind of
conversations that you end up having
with the AI based on this. If I want to
turn this into an issue that my AFK
agent picks up, I can use two PRD or two
issues here. And by the way, if you're
interested in these skills that I'm
talking about, then you should check out
this site here, which is linked below.
I'm going to be creating a real
documentation site for these skills, and
for now, I have a newsletter that you
can sign up to for the latest updates,
as well as tips and tricks and resources
for getting the most out of agents. The
thing that's important to notice here is
just how much this skill demands of you,
the user. This is not an AFK skill that
you can just sort of run and kind of
like uh just rely on to continually
improve your code base. This requires a
judgment call from you, the programmer
sitting above the LLM. I think of agents
as really, really good tactical
programmers. They're able to get on the
ground and make changes quickly. But
they need someone on the level above
them who is the strategic programmer.
And that's what this skill does. It
allows the sergeant to go and run around
the code base and look for potential
improvement
opportunities. But then you, the
general, have to go and actually make
the change and decide what's good for
the long-term health of the code base. I
recommend that you run this skill, you
know, every couple of days, really.
Especially in a code base that's
fast-moving, you're going to come up
with tons
for deepening the code base. And the
deeper you get those modules, the higher
leverage you're going to get out of
them. And leverage as well means
testing. If you have a set of really
nice clear seams in your code base, then
you're going to be able to write really
nice tests around those nice deep
modules. And the better your tests are,
the better the output from the agent is
going to be. One final thought here is
that lots of folks ask me how you would
get started by using AI in a legacy code
base. And a legacy code base is probably
going to have a lot of shallow modules.
It's I mean, we talk about legacy code
bases, what we really mean are bad code
bases. Code bases that are hard to make
changes in. And what you really need
before you start making changes in a
legacy code base is a harness around the
code base to make sure that your changes
don't mess anything up. So for that, you
need tests, test, testing really nice
deep modules that have a lot of leverage
and locality. So running improve code
base architecture is a great place to
start. Thanks for watching, folks, and I
hope that answers some of your questions
about how to solve this never-ending
problem of AI just running away and
creating terrible code bases. I hope you
enjoy the skills. Do follow the link
below if you want to find more of them.
So thanks for watching and I'll see you
in the next one. And what you really
need before you start making changes in
a legacy code bases